Guide to the James E. Dittes Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
James E. Dittes Papers
1944-2003
RG 174
Yale University Divinity School Library
4.5
(9 boxes)
This collection documents the academic career of Yale professor James E. Dittes. Dittes received his B.D. and Ph.D. from Yale and taught Pastoral Theology and the Psychology of Religion at Yale beginning in 1955.
Dittes, James E.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James E. Dittes
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1926 December 26 Born in Cleveland, Ohio
1949 B.A., Oberlin College
1954 B.D., Yale University Divinity School
1955 M.S., Yale University, Department of Psychology
1958 Ph.D., Yale University, Department of Psychology
1955-68 Instructor to Associate Professor, Psychology of Religion, Yale University
1959-65 Executive Secretary, Society for the Scientific Study of Religion
1966-71 Editor, Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion
1968-84 Professor, Psychology of Religion, Yale University
1969-75 Director of Graduate Studies, Department of Religious Studies, Yale University
1975-82 Chairperson, Department of Religious Studies, Yale University
1984-2002 Professor, Pastoral Theology and Psychology, Yale University
2009 August 24 Died in Hamden, CT
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Course-Related Materials
IV. Personal and Biographical material
These papers were given to the library by Prof. Dittes as he approached retirement. They document his long and noteworthy academic career at Yale. Series I, Correspondence, provides a glimpse of issues and activities that have been important to Dittes over the past half century. Series II, Writings, includes sermons, talks, lectures, published articles, papers written while Dittes was a student, unpublished papers, and reviews. Series III, Course-Related Materials, provides a good overview of courses taught by Dittes from 1955 to 1999. Series IV, Personal and Biographical Material, includes autobiographical writings and other material documenting Dittes' life and work.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Course-Related Materials
IV. Personal and Biographical material
Pastoral theology; Educators; Dittes, James E.; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, Series I
  - General
    - ATS Executive Director Candidacy, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Brewster, Kingman, Jr, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Community Activities, 1949-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dispute over Oberlin College governance, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Donald Capp Correspondence, re. special issue of Pastoral Psychology, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 124)
    - In Parish Pastoral Studies Program, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 122)
    - Job Search, 1979-1981 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Letters to editors, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - National Organizations, 1944-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - On-site school evaluations, 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pastoral, 1955-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Famous", 1960-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript Evaluations
    - Correspondence re. Journal for Scientific Study of Religion (JSSR), notes and manuscript rejections, 1966-1971 (Box 9, Folder 139)
    - Correspondence re. Journal for Scientific Study of Religion (JSSR), letters encourging revision for publication, 1966-1971 (Box 9, Folder 140)
    - Various, 1960-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
    - Various, 1977-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Yale-related
    - Curriculum Committee, 1964-65 (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Beecher Lectureship, including Garrison Keillor correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 126)
    - Discussions of YDS policies and programs, 1959-1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Dissertation Reports, 1972-1982 (Box 9, Folder 120)
    - Leave salary, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Lee Keck correspondence, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Ministry Studies Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 123)
    - Old Testament Appointment, Bonnie Kittel, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 128)
    - Study of cults, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 127)
    - Terry Lectureship, 1974-1982 (Box 9, Folder 125)
    - Re. Divinity students in Psych 37b, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Re. Leon Watts, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Writings, Series II
  - Sermons, lectures, talks
    - Various, 1960-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18-27)
    - Various, 1979-1999 (Box 3, Folder 28-38)
  - Booklength
    - Bibliography of writings which appear in books (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Chinese Translation of The Male Predicament (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Articles
    - Bibliography of Articles (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "A Child-Centered Culture" from Children's Religion (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "A Men's Movement for the Church?" from The Christian Century; "Analytical (Jungian) Psychology and Pastoral Care" from Dictionary of Pastoral Care and Counseling (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "A Symposium on Pastoral Research" from The Journal of Pastoral Care (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "Galvanic Skin Response as a Measure of Patient's Reaction to Therapist's Permissiveness" from Abnormal and Social Psychology (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "Affiliation:Comparability or Compatibility?" (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "Anatomy of Anxiety" from The Connecticut State Medical Journal; "Attractiveness of Group as Function of Self-Esteem and Acceptance of Group" from The Journal of Abnormal and Special Psychology; "Beyond William James" from Beyond the Classics? Essays in the Scientific Study of Religion (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Biographical/Theological Exegesis of Psychological Texts:The Case of Freud's Search for 'After-Life'" from Religion and Social Order (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - "Birth Order and Vulnerability to Differences in Acceptance" (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - "Birth Order as a Selective Factor Among Volunteer Subjects" from Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology; "Boison as Autobiographer: Unblinking but Unseeing" from Journal of Psychology and Christianity (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "Breakdown of Society" and "Opinion Pollster" from Theological Education (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - "Changes in Layman's Expectations of the Minister's Role" from Ministry Studies (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - "Conceptual Deprivation and Statistical Rigor: Comment on 'Social Deprivation and Religiosity'" from Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion; "Confessing Away the Soul with the Sins, or: The Risks of Uncle Tomism Among the HUmanists. A Reply to Robert Bellah" from Council on the Study of Religion (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - "Continuities between the Life and Thought of Augustine" from Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion; "Effects of Changes in Self Esteem Upon Impulsiveness and Deliberation in Making Judgements" from The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - "Effects of Different Conditions of Acceptance Upon Conformity to Group Norms" from The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - "Effects of Manipulated Self-Esteem on Persuasibility Depending on Threat and Complexity of Communication" from Journal of Personality and Social Psychology; "Extinction during Psychotherapy of GSR Accompanying 'Embarrasing Statements'" from The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - "Face Impression Study - Correlation of TSI Scores with Student Self-Report of Motivation and With Interviewer Rating" (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - "Facts and Fantasy in (the Minister's) Mental Health" from Pastoral Psychology; "Foreword" from A Study of Generations (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - "Impulsive Closure as Reaction to Failure-Induced Threat" from Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - "In Relation to All Psychology" from Pastoral Psychology; "Justification by Faith and the Experimental Psychologist" Religion in Life (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - "Now it Came to Pass That..." from The Pulpit (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - "On the Need for Control in Persuasive Scientific Communications" from Psychology Reports; "Pastoral Implications" December 1989, March 1990, February 1991, and April 1991 from Lectionary Homiletics; "Pastoral Theology on the West Bank: Reflections on Seminary Politics" from Journal of Pastoral Theology (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - "Philosophy of Learning and Character" from Religious Education; "Previous Studies on Content Analysis of Psychotherapy", Appendix A from Scoring Human Motives: A Manual (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - "Psychology of Religion" from Handbook of Social Psychology; "Psychology and a Ministry of Faith" from The Ministry and Mental Health (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - "'Reason for Being' at Union and Yale" from The Christian Century; "Recollections of the Adolescence and Young Adulthood of the SSSR" from Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - "Relation of TSI Scores and Selected Items of Biographical Information"; "Release from Idolatry" from New Conversations (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - "Religion: Maker of Bonds and Boundaries" from Papers in Comparative Studies; "Religion, Prejudice, and Personality" from Research on Religious Development (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - "Religious Education Beyond Religion" from Religious Education (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - "Research on Clergymen:Factors Influencing Decisions for Religious Service and Effectiveness in the Vocation"; "Science vs. Religion." from Psychologia et Sociologia Religionum (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - "Secular Religion:Dilemma of Churches and Researchers" from Religious Research (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - "The Symbolic Value of Celibacy for the Catholic Faithful" from Concilium:Theology in the Age of Renewal (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - "Teachings and Research" from Council on the Study of Religion (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - "The Christian Mission and Turkish Islam" from The Muslim World (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - "The Effect of Cognitive Ambiguity on Anxiety and Affiliative Preference"; "The Investigator as an Instrument of Investigation: Some Explanatory Observations on the Compleat Researcher" from Encounter with Erikson (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - "The Male Role Denies Men's Needs" from Yale Weekly Bulletin and Calendar (Box 9, Folder 129)
    - "The Ministry of Merging Divinity Schools"; "The Mitigated Self from The Endangered Self (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - "The Relevance of Being Irrelevant" from The Princeton Seminary Bulletin (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - "To Accept and To Celebrate Conflict" from Ministry Studies; "Tracking God's Call: Basic Theoretical Issues in Clergy Assessment" from Clergy Assessment and Career Development; "Two Issues in Measuring Religion" from Research on Religious Development (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - "Typing the Typologies: Some Parallels in the Career of Church-sect and Extrinsic-Instinsic" from Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - "Using the Mind to Show the Soul" from Contemporary Psychology (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - "Who Calls us 'Healer'?" from The Christian Ministry; "Why Conflicts?" from Growth in Ministry (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Three articles derived from PhD dissertation - "Attraction of Group as Functions of Self-Esteem and Acceptance by Group" and "Effect of Changes in Self-Esteem Upon Impulsiveness and Deliberation in Making Judgments" and "Justification by Faith and the Experimental Psychologist" (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Reviews
    - Reviews and Bibliography of Reviews (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Student Papers (by JED)
    - Papers, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Papers, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 84-88)
    - Papers, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - PhD dissertation, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Unpublished Writings and Notes
    - Various inc. Estonians, Yale Study on Roommate Selection, Space Relations Test Materials, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Various inc. Different Effects of Manipulated Self-Esteem on Persuasibility, Careers of Rockefeller Brothers Fellows At Yale Divinity School, 1954-62, 1961-62 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Various inc. Effects of social Comparison vs. social support, the effect of cognitive ambiguity and affiliative preference, closure as a factor in persuasability, proposal of project for Guggenheim fellowship, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Various inc. Apostle's Summons (poem), Definition as a process of perceptual differentiation, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Various inc. Definition as a process of perceptual differentiation, Sam: Artful Decommitter, Does religion celebrate or compensate?, Defensive Functions of Cognititve Closure Terminal Progress Report, Research Proposals in the Psychology of Religion, The Utility of Psychological Tests for Theological Students, Continuities between the life and thought of selected religious thinkers, book proposals, notes re. religion, notes re. catholic priesthood, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Various inc. Ministry: Starkness at Noon, Spiritual Life Development: Between Captivity and the Promised Land, What Kind of Persons Become Ministers?, Belief as a Mark of Religionless Religion, 1974-1978 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - Various inc. notes re. dissapointment of congregations with their clergy, writing journal, seminar proposals "the function of religion as a choreographer of bonds", "Freedom and the Religious Personality", "The 'Theologies' of Freud and Jung", 1980-1986 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Various inc. About Men: Approximations, Psychology of Religion, Some strategies for mitigating psychoanalysis' antagonism to religion, 1988-1991 (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - Various inc. NEH Summer Seminar "Augustine and Jung: Paradigmatic Religious Thinkers in Autobiography", notes: autobiographical, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - Original Manuscript, "An Article on Turkish Mission", 1952 (Box 9, Folder 135)
    - Unfinished Manuscript, "BELT", Re. commitment, alienation, etc., tentatively titled "When Idols Crumble", n. d. (Box 9, Folder 136)
    - Notes, Re. Freud esp. Moses & Maimonides, 1988-1999 (Box 9, Folder 137)
    - Notes, Re. commitment and alienation, 1970-1979 (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Tributes
    - Various, 1968, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 100)
- Course-Related Materials, Series III
  - Student paper comments, grades (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - 30A Psychology of Religion, 1959-1991 (Box 7, Folder 102-104)
  - 160A Psychological Foundations of Personality, 1955-1962 (Box 7, Folder 105-106)
  - 310A Personality and Religion, 1962-1968 (Box 7, Folder 107-108)
  - 310B Personality and Religion, 1963-1969 (Box 9, Folder 130)
  - 865B Psychology of Religion, 1950-2000: a personal retrospective, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 131)
  - 868B Moses and Maimonides, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 132)
  - 908A Pastoral Counseling, 1997-1999 (Box 9, Folder 133)
  - 908B Pastoral Counseling, 1996-1999 (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - 963B The Persona of the Preacher and Other Preaching Classes, 1987-1991 (Box 9, Folder 134)
  - Options in Faith and Ministry course, 1981-1987 (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Miscellaneous courses (Box 8, Folder 111)
- Personal and Autobiographical Material, Series IV
  - General (Box 8, Folder 112)
  - Essay in Psychology and Faith: The Christian Experience of Eighteen Psychologists, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 113)
  - Personal statement requesting ordination, n. d. (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Transcript from interview, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - "Some Accidents, Coincidents, and Intents: A Vocational Narrative" for Pastoral Psychology, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 115)
  - Bound volume of letters to Dittes from colleagues and friends: "Professor James E. Dittes: Witness to Healing and Hope", 2002 (Box 9, Folder 141)